玄黄端现 太极混沌如鸡蛋
In the beginning, there was darkness...
随着轰的一声
and then, bang...
诞生了无限膨胀的时间 空间和物质
giving birth to an endless expanding existence...of time, space, and matter.
现在所见超乎我们的想象
Now, see further than we've ever imagined...
超越了客观认知极限
beyond the limits of our existence...
那地方我们称之为"宇宙"
in a place we call "The Universe."
这或许是行星科学的圣杯
lt's perhaps the holy grail of planetary science.
我们是宇宙中独一无二的吗？
Are we alone in the universe?
这是我们要回答的最重大的问题之一
lt's one of the grandest questions we could answer.
我们其实并没有生命的定义
We don't really have a definition of life...
但是 我认为发现之时就会知道了
but l think l'll know it when l discover it.
生命可能会迂回曲折
Life can take many twists and turns...
我认为它最酷的地方
and l think the really cool thing about it...
就是我们有可能在别处看到的种类
is the variety that we're going to be able to find else where.
我们是一颗孤独的行星 抑或地球以外还有生命存在？
Are we a lonely planet, or does life exist beyond Earth?
天体生物学前沿领域的同仁们
Members of the groundbreaking field of astrobiology...
已经联合起来共同解决这个未解之谜
havejoined forces to solve this enduring mystery.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://cmct.cc
影片压制:春树  字幕来源:五羊皮  调校:御雪寒狼  招募Q号:76846146
[历史频道] 第二季 第七集 天体生物学
[History Channel] The UniverseⅡ 07of19 Astrobiology
生命 在宇宙中是否是十分罕见的
Life, is it rare in our universe...
还是就在银河动物园里挤满了各种生物呢？
or is space a galactic zoo, teeming with all sorts of creatures?
大家都对外星生命有着这种图像化的概念
Everybody has this sort of iconic view of the aliens.
他们都是些阴沉的小家伙 大大的眼睛 小小的鼻子
They're going to be little gray guys with big eyeballs and small noses.
或许是这样 但是 我不这么认为
Well, maybe, but l don't think so.
在遥远的行星上 生命没准就是贼眼大大的微生物
On far-off planets, life may be as far out as buggy-eyed microbes...
或者就是银河蝠鲼之类的科幻海怪
or sci-fi sea monsters like galactic manta rays.
其它则可归类为神经机械有机体
Others may be home to cybernetic organisms...
生物和机械的混血儿
hybrids of biology and machines.
理清超级高等外星生命思路的一个方法
One way to get a handle on thinking about super advanced aliens...
就是尝试想象一下我们自己未来的情景
is to try to imagine the possibilities of our own future.
也许会是机器复合人
Maybe it'll be machine-enabled humans.
我感觉自己已经成了机器复合人了
l feel like l've already become a machine-human hybrid.
我的意思是 我这台随身携带的手提电脑
l mean, l have this laptop computer that l take with me everywhere...
它俨然成了我大脑的第三半区了
which is really kind of the third hemisphere of my brain.
我身体甚至都在逐步变成
My body is even changing...
用手提电脑那种人的外形了
and becoming sort of shaped like a person using a laptop computer...
因此 我正在变成人机复合体
and so l'm becoming a Homo laptopicus.
有可能宇宙到处都存在着生命
lt's likely that the universe is full of life.
我们尚无法证明我们不是孤独的
We don't have evidence yet that we're not alone.
所以我们来到那里 来看看
So we're out there, and we're looking.
提起搜寻外星生命
When it comes to hunting for alien life...
行星科学家 音乐家戴维·格林斯彭
planetary scientist and musician David Grinspoon...
弹奏出不同的节奏
walks to a different beat.
我就想知道关于外星生命
l do wonder, in terms of extraterrestrial life...
是否有音乐或音乐之类的东西
whether they'll have music or something like music.
音乐本质上是声波和韵律
Music is fundamentally waves and rhythms...
属于我们宇宙的本性
and that's sort of the nature of our universe.
事实上是某种乐感
There is a certain musicality ofjust the fact...
就是所有的颤动 声波 韵律 音调
that it's all vibrations and waves and rhythms and modulated tones.
所以 我可以想象出 当然这只是我的异想天开
So l can imagine, and this is just my wild fantasy...
比方说遥远未来的世界音乐
some analogy to world music far in the future...
就是我们的音乐文化和外星音乐文化交织在一起
where we're mixing our musical cultures with alien musical cultures.
我想你要是与不同的科学家交流
l think you'll get many different shades of astrobiology...
就会看到天体生物学的各种差异
if you talk to different scientists...
但是 在大致的目标上我认为你我会有很多共识
but l think you'll get a lot of agreement on the broad goals.
我们希望发现外星生命 但是同时
We want to find life else where, but in the meantime...
我们对地球的生命史 还仍有待进一步认识
we're learning a lot about the history of life on Earth.
在天体生物学领域里
ln the field of astrobiology...
搜寻外星生命的重要目标之一
one of the fundamental goals in searching for life else where...
就是首先要搞明白地球生命是如何演化的
is first figuring out how life evolved here on Earth.
天体生物学一个重大的未解之谜
One of the big unsolved mysteries in astrobiology, of course...
当然就是生命何以在地球上诞生
is how life got started on Earth...
因为 我们一旦搞明白了我们就能够洞察
because if we can understand that, then we would have some insight...
生命是否已经能够诞生于别的地方
into whether it could have gotten started else where.
地球运行于所谓的适居带"habitable zone"
Earth orbits in what's called the "habitable zone."
这个太空区域的环境有利于生命的形成
lt's a region of space where conditions are favorable for life forms...
这些我们知道都能在地球上看到
that we know can be found on our planet.
我们刚好处于与太阳适当的距离
We are at just the right distance from the Sun...
所以我们的海洋不会蒸发掉
so our oceans don't evaporate...
我们的温度不太冷也不太热
our temperatures are not too hot or too cold...
我们在大气层里有氧气所以我们能够呼吸
and we have oxygen in our atmosphere so we can breathe.
地球一直是各种生命的宇宙天堂
Earth's been a cosmic paradise for all types of life...
从小的单细胞生物如细菌
from small single-celled organisms, such as bacteria...
到大的多细胞哺乳动物 包括人类
to large multicellular mammals, including man.
据认为我们地球的所有生命
lt's believed that all life on our planet...
都是传承于约34到38亿年前的
descended from a single common microbial ancestry...
一个共同的微生物老祖宗
approximately 3.4 to 3.8 billion years ago.
但是那个微生物是如何开始的始终是个谜
But how that microbe came into being remains puzzling.
寻求答案的一个方法就是寻找古代岩石
One way to search for answers is to look for ancient rocks...
那里微生物会留下它们生存的蛛丝马迹
where microbes leave trace evidence of their existence.
地质学是了解地球生命起源和进化的关键手段
Geology is a crucial tool...for understanding the origins and evolution of life on Earth...
因为地球生命的历史记载
because the historical record of life on Earth...
几乎完整地记录在我们脚下的岩石里
is almost entirely recorded in the rocks that we walk on.
地质学家阿比盖尔·奥尔伍德的生命起源发现之旅
GeologistAbigail Allwood'sjourney to discover the origins of life...
走出并没有超出她自己后院有多远
took her no farther than her own backyard.
西澳大利亚的皮尔巴拉地区
The Pilbara region ofWestAustralia...
含有一些地球上最古老的岩石
contains some of the oldest rocks on our planet.
它们几乎有35亿岁了
They're almost 3 1/2 billion years old.
皮尔巴拉含有太古代早期的岩石
The Pilbara contains rocks from the earlyArchean era...
在地球上保留至今
that have survived on the Earth today.
其中的一些岩石单位有可能含有生命的迹象
They contain several rock units that contain possible evidence for life.
地球已经存在了46亿年了
Planet Earth has been around for over4.6 billion years.
然而其最原始的地表大部分已经
But most of its original surface has been obliterated...
被地块构造和风化抹去了
by plate tectonics and erosion.
皮尔巴拉极厚的地壳
The extremely thick crust in the Pilbara...
帮助它抵御破坏性的地质过程
has helped it resist destructive geologic processes.
皮尔巴拉没有受到板块构造的强烈影响
The Pilbara hasn't been strongly affected by plate tectonics...
水成岩里的原始特征
and the original features in the sedimentary rocks...
差不多准备让我们去解读
are more or less ready for us to interpret.
在南非还有一些同时代的水成岩
There are also sedimentary rocks of similar age...
几乎有35亿岁了
almost 3 1/2 billion years old, in South Africa.
迄今为止皮尔巴拉似乎已经带来了丰富的化石记录
So far the Pilbara seems to have yielded a richerfossil record.
奥尔伍德化了三年多的时间
Allwood spent more than three years...
勘察皮尔巴拉的一些岩层
surveying some of the rock formations in the Pilbara...
研究叫做叠层石罕见构造
examining unusual structures called stromatolites...
35亿年前生物所形成的化石
fossils formed by living organisms 3 1/2 billion years ago.
我们意识到我们要寻找的
We realized that what we were looking at...
是古礁石上的残骸 微生物礁石
was the remnants of an ancient reef, a microbial reef.
它不是我们今天所熟悉的那种珊瑚形成的礁石
lt's not a reef made of coral like we're familiar with today...
而是叠层石形成的礁石 由微生物所形成的构造
but a reef made of stromatolites, structures formed by microorganisms.
叠层石是形成于海底的岩石构造
Stromatolites are rocky structures that form on the sea floor...
在那里一层层纤细的沉积物 长期以来借助于微生物
where fine layers of sediment are built up into cones, domes...
逐步形成了圆锥状 馒头状和其他形状
and other shapes over a long time with the help of tiny organisms.
叠层石并没有生命
A stromatolite is not alive...
然而其构造却是由活体形成的
but is a structure made by living things.
一旦我们在化石记录中找到一个
When we find one in the fossil record...
那就像是找到了死去已久的微生物的足迹
it is like finding the footprint of long-dead microorganisms.
但是微生物本身几乎从来就不会作为化石
But the microbes themselves are almost never preserved as fossils...
保存在叠层石里头
inside the stromatolites.
否则要确定古叠层石作为生命的证据
And without that, it is extremely difficult to be sure...
是极其困难的
an ancient stromatolite is proof of life.
但是在这里 奥尔伍德发现了皮尔巴拉的叠层石里
But in this case, Allwood found that the Pilbara stromatolites...
实实在在的生物
are, in fact, biological.
她或许已经发现了我们地球上最古老生命的迹象
She just may have discovered the oldest evidence of life on our planet.
这些叠层石是地球生命令人信服的最古老的证据
These stromatolites are the oldest convincing evidence of life on Earth.
这些神奇的圆锥形构造里面
ln these amazing pronounced conical structures...
并不像你在海底可以看到的那些根本
that are not like any kind of wave ripple or a structure that you'd expect to see on the sea floor...
并不存在生物的波痕或构造
where there's no biology.
这些被标注为叠层石的
These are interpreted as stromatolites...
沉积物构造是微生物形成的
sedimentary structures formed by microorganisms...
它们生活在沉积物与海洋的分界面上
that lived at the interface between the sediment and the ocean.
奥尔伍德利用地质技术来了解
Allwood used geological techniques to interpret the environment...
这些变成了化石的微生物当时可能生活在
these fossilized microorganisms may have lived in...
将近35亿年前的环境
almost 3 1/2 billion years ago.
我们看到的恰好是叠层石形成之前的东西
What we saw was that...immediately before the stromatolites formed...
差不多就在这坚硬的海岸线上
was a setting pretty much just like this, a rocky coastline.
我们看到叠层石只存在于浅水环境中
We see that the stromatolites only exist in the shallow-water environment...
并不存在于当时已经存在的深水区里
and don't exist in the deep-water areas that were existing at the same time.
这种化石化的生态系统提供了回头一瞥
This fossilized ecosystem provides a glimpse into the past...
那可能就是人类最早祖先的遗迹
and what might be the remains of man's earliest ancestors.
随着天体生物学以及
With the rise of astrobiology...
了解生命证据的新技术 新手段的发展
and new techniques and approaches to interpret evidence for life...
我们可以相当有把握地说生命诞生于地球
we can be fairly confident about saying that life was on Earth...
至少是在34.3亿年前
at least 3,430 million years ago.
然而生命会不会比我们的地球更早出现呢？
But could life have existed even earlier on our planet?
生命最古老的证据并不证明最古老的生命
The oldest evidence of life is not evidence of the oldest life.
我们并没有地球史开头5亿年的任何地质记录
We do not have any geologic record...for the first half billion years of Earth's history...
所以有一大堆东西没了踪影
so there's a whole bunch of stuff missing.
化石记录里没有保存的东西
What's not preserved in the fossil record...
就是生命一开始是怎么形成的
is how life formed in the first place.
我们人类是星尘的后裔
We humans are the descendants of stardust.
46亿年前恒星碎片在我们的太阳系里
4.6 billion years ago, stellar debris created vast clouds of gas...
创造了巨大的气体云
within our solar system.
这些气体云形成了尘粒并相互粘贴在一起
These gaseous clouds formed dust particles, which stuck together.
它们最终形成了很大的漂石
They eventually formed large boulders...
由岩石和冰构成 叫做小行星和彗星
made of rock and ice called asteroids and comets.
在数百万年里
For millions of years...
这些物体碰撞 兼并形成了包括地球在内的众多行星
these bodies collided and coalesced to form planets, including Earth.
在这种重创期间地球是一个炙热 有毒的水世界
During this heavy bombardment, Earth was a hot, toxic waterworld.
然而在这个动荡年代中
But in the midst of this volatile period...
生命有可能已经占据了海面下的
life may have taken hold below the ocean surface...
火山附近的热水口
in hydrothermal vents, which are formed near volcanoes.
在那里环境中的化学和能量
There, atmospheric chemicals and energy...
有可能已经形成了生命的要素 氨基酸的混合物
may have formed a cocktail of amino acids...the essential elements of life.
普遍的假设之一
One of the popular hypotheses...
是生命起源于热水口附近
is that life arose around a hydrothermal vent...
因为那里的特殊环境
because of the particular conditions there...
有可能是深水环境
that it would've been a deeper-water environment...
提供了对撞击的防护
which offers protection from impact.
浅水环境在重创期间可能会相当不安全
Shallow-water environments would have been very hostile...during the period of heavy bombardment.
然而天体生物学的关键问题是
But the key question for astrobiology is...
把非生命的物质变成生命物质的火花究竟在那里呢？
where did the spark occur that took nonliving matter...and turns it into living matter?
克里斯·麦凯是天体生物学领域的佼佼者
Chris McKay is a giant in the field of astrobiology.
这个航天局的科学家历经25个年头
The NASA scientist has spent over twenty-five years...
试图破解地球生命的起源并在别处找到它
trying to decode the origin of life on Earth and find it else where.
有整套理论
There's a whole set of theories...
提出生命开始以及在地球上诞生所需的一切
that suggests that everything needed for life...started and was created here on Earth.
因此导致第一个生命的有机物质
So the organic material that led to the first life...
可能产生于地球上的闪电
could have been produced in lightning discharges on Earth.
另一个理论认为导致生命的有机物
An alternative theory is that the organics that led to life...
不是地球上产生的而是舶来物
weren't created on Earth, but came into Earth.
比如彗星就可能是有机物的源头
Comets, for example, could be a source of organics.
来自火星或小行星的陨石坠落
Meteorites from Mars or asteroid infall...
可能会是有机物的来源
could have been a source for organics.
所以原材料是外来的 而生命却还是地道土特产
So now the raw materials are imported, but life is still homegrown.
然而还有一个理论认为
Yet another theory suggests...
不仅生命的有机物是输入的
that not only did the organics for life come in...
而且生命本身也有可能是来自外太空
but life itself might have come in from outer space.
我们真的不知道如何在这三个选项中做出选择
We don't really know how to choose between those three alternatives.
构成地球上所有生命的基本原料
All life on Earth is made up of essential building blocks...
包括碳 氢 氧 氮
including carbon, hydrogen, oxygen, and nitrogen...
还有二十来个其它成分
as well as two dozen other ingredients.
但是最基本的东西似乎是水和碳
But the fundamental properties appear to be water and carbon.
生物的碳水模式是我们熟悉的东西
The carbon-and-water model of biology is the one that we're familiar with...
似乎是生物运转的最佳途径
and it seems to be the best way for biology to operate.
科学家认为寻找外星生命最大的可能
Scientists think the best chance forfinding extraterrestrial life...
就是搜寻我们太阳里的行星上的碳 水痕迹
is to search for traces of carbon and water...on planets in our own solar system.
水星与金星离太阳太近了
Mercury and Venus are too close to our sun...
难以维持液态水或地球一样的大气层
to sustain liquid water or an Earthlike atmosphere.
那么火星 这距离太阳第四颗行星又怎样呢？
But what about Mars, the fourth planet from the Sun?
研究地球生命最古老的证据
Studying the oldest evidence for life on Earth...
关系到搜寻火星生命
is relevant to the search for life on Mars.
我们拥有有力的证据 在过去某个时期…
We have strong evidence that some time in the past...
火星可能较为好客热情
Mars may have been more hospitable...
较为温暖湿润 存在大气层
wetter and warmer, had an atmosphere.
如今 火星看上去就像是一个尘土飞扬的红色不毛之地
Today, Mars looks like a dusty red desert.
其大气层非常稀薄且表面的液态水
lts atmosphere is so thin that liquid water...
同时被冻结和蒸发
would freeze and evaporate at the same time on its surface.
然而火星的地貌显示出极地冰盖 沟壑 火山
But Mars' topography reveals polar ice caps, gullies, and volcanoes...
包括太阳系里最大的奥林匹斯山
including Olympus Mons, the largest in the solar system.
那么液态水会存在于温度较高的地表下吗？
So could liquid water still exist beneath the surface...where temperatures are warmer?
科学家认为找到地球以外的生命的最大可能
Scientists believe the best chance forfinding life beyond planet Earth...
有可能成为太阳系的下一扇大门
might be next door in our solar system.
火星 太阳的第四个岩石星球
Mars, the fourth rock from the Sun...
可能在其地下存在液态水
may have liquid water beneath its surface...
生命的一个很好的迹象
a good signature for life.
火星上可能确实存在水热系统
Hydrothermal systems can definitely exist on Mars...
因为我们可以看到大量的火山
because we can see massive volcanoes.
我们知道火星表面存在有大量的水
We know there's plenty of water still on the surface of Mars.
热源 水源
That heat source, the water source...
提供了让微生物快乐生存所必需的所有要素
provides all the ingredients necessary...to make microbial life very happy.
为了更好地了解火星的地质情况
To better understand the geology on Mars...
天体生物学家艾德里安·布朗博士调查地球上的热点地区
astrobiologist Dr. Adrian Brown investigates the hot spots on Earth...
尤其是北加州的拉森火山国家公园
particularly Lassen Volcanic National Park in northern California.
我对拉森火山公园感兴趣的原因
The reason l'm interested in Lassen Volcanic Park...
是因为这些水热热点地区
is because of these hydrothermal hot spot areas...
在这里我们可以看到正在形成的矿物质
where we can find minerals that are forming...
除了这里不会形成于其他地方
that don't form anywhere else but these areas.
这些富含硫酸盐的矿物质你看堆积在这山丘两侧
These sulfate-rich minerals that you see in the sides of the hills here...
这里我们认为类似于火星
are areas that we think that are analogous to Mars.
它们现在依然很活跃的事实
And the fact that they're still active today...
意味着我们可以获得它们对于生命有多友好的概念
means that we can get an idea of howfriendly they are for life.
水热温泉形成于火山附近
Hydrothermal hot springs are formed near volcanoes.
在地下深处炙热的火山岩浆库
Deep underground, the searing heat ofvolcanic magma chambers...
将热水挤压且把矿物质溶解
propels hot water and dissolved minerals...
进入地表的裂缝里
into cracks and fissures in the subsurface...
然后喷发出地面
which then erupts onto the surface of the Earth.
温泉周围堆积着的符合微生物口味的
The spring surrounds itself with a treasure trove...
富含能量的矿物质
of energy-laden minerals suitable for a microbial feast.
就像我身后的这个热水泉
A hydrothermal spring, just like the one behind me here...
将完全会是我们登陆火星的理想之地
would be exactly the place that we'd want to land on Mars.
这种区域行很适合生命的生存
This sort of area would be just perfect for life to exist...
甚至适合生命的形成和诞生
perhaps even for life to form, the origins of life.
这个地方水通过管道源源不断压出了
This area where water has been forced up through conduits...
将矿物质 能源带出地表
and carried along minerals, energy sources, to the surface...
然后分布在沉淀物四周
and then spread them out around the deposit...
为微生物提供了能源的来源
for microbes to feed on as an energy source.
布朗认为如果火星上还有火山活动
Brown thinks if Mars is still volcanically active...
那么类似的水热区域有会存在
similar hydrothermal areas will exist.
那些地方就有可能已诞生生命
They might be places where life may have originated...
或就存在于地表下方
or still exists just below the surface.
我们在轨道上观察火星是颗红色的行星
Mars is a red planet that we see from orbit.
然而就在其薄薄的一层尘埃下面
But just underneath a thin layer of dust...
我们观察到了一大片富含硅酸盐的矿物质
we see a whole rich array of sulfate-rich minerals...
许多科学家认为有可能已经形成了热液
that many scientists believe may have been formed hydrothermally.
我们看到的那些非常类似于
And we see those very similar minerals...
在拉森这里我们周围的岩石和山丘里的矿物质
in the rocks and the hills surrounding us here at Lassen.
2006年航天局的火星勘测轨道飞行器抵达了红色星球
ln 2006, NASA's Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter probe arrived at the red planet.
它装备有集成型火星勘测成像光谱仪
lt's equipped...with the Compact Reconnaissance lmaging Spectrometerfor Mars...
简称CRlSM 该计划颠覆了我们对火星的看法
better known as CRlSM, which plans to revolutionize our view of the planet.
利用可见光和红外线
Using visible and infrared light...
仪器一直在扫描水手谷里的古代液态水的痕迹
the instrument has been scanning for evidence of ancient liquid water...
那是一个巨大的峡谷系统
in Valles Marineris, a massive canyon system...
被奥林帕斯火山撕裂了表面
ripped into the surface by the volcano Olympus Mons.
那里可能存有水热沉淀物
The area may hold hydrothermal deposits.
火星此时未必很活跃
Mars is unlikely to be active at the moment.
然而在其活跃期有可能存在过热水
But in its active phase, it may have been that hydrothermal waters...
是由我们今天所看到大量的火山所驱动的
were driven by the massive volcanoes that we see on Mars today.
火星可能形成过活跃的水热系统
And Mars may have been able to form...
和这个一样
active hydrothermal systems, such as this...
在火星的表面堆积成厚厚的一层硅酸盐矿物质
and build up a rich layer of sulfate minerals on the surface of Mars.
早期的火星要比现在的火星更适合人居
Early Mars was much more habitable than the current-day Mars.
火星冷却了
The planet cooled off.
它现在太冷 太干燥了不足以维持生命
lt's now too cold and too dry to support life.
因此如果火星上有过早期生命的话
So if there was early life on Mars...
可能已不再其表面了
it's probably not on the surface anymore...
极有可能已经迁徙到了地下
and it could potentially have migrated into the subsurface...
进入了地下的宜居环境中
into inhabitable environments below the ground.
研究员詹妮佛·赫德曼
Research scientist Jennifer Heldmann...
也在积极探索火星生命
is also on a quest to find life on Mars...
通过了解微生物是如何
by understanding how microscopic organisms...
生存于地球的极端环境中的
survive in extreme environments on Earth.
然而并非研究地球上的热点地区
But instead of investigating the hot spots on our planet...
而是在寒冷地带搜寻生命
she scours for life in cold places.
眼下 尤其是在拉森火山公园
Right now, specifically at Lassen Volcanic Park...
我们观察积雪堆积物
we are looking at snowpack deposits...
我们对这些积雪特别感兴趣
and we're especially interested in these snowpacks...
因为有雪生藻类生活在其中
because they have snow algae living in them.
因此到了晚春 夏季
So in the late spring, summer months...
你可以看到积雪被染成了鲜红色
you'll see the snowpacks colored bright red...
斑斑红色透过积雪
streaks and ribbons of red running through the snowpack.
那就是藻类
And that's the algae.
所以这些积雪里实际上是存在着生命的
So there's actually life living in these snowpacks.
所以我们研究雪生藻类适宜生存的物理环境
And so we're studying the physical conditions...that the snow algae like to live in...
将这应用于火星的积雪带
and applying that to snowpacks on Mars...
来观察火星可能存在的积雪里面是否有同样的环境
to see if the same conditions within snowpacks on Mars might exist.
航天局的火星环球探测者号最近发现火星的沟壑
NASA's Mars Global Surveyor has recently discovered Martian gullies...
可能是古积雪的遗迹
that could be the ancient remains of snowpacks.
我们边观察边研究这些现象
We're looking at these to study this phenomenon.
那些积雪会不会融化变成液态水？
Can those snowpacks actually melt, generate liquid water...
同时有可能为生命提供一个宜居的环境呢？
and also potentially provide habitable environments for life?
为了更好地了解火星上的积雪
To better understand snowpacks on Mars...
赫德曼在拉森火山公园进行了实验
Heldmann conducts experiments in Lassen Volcanic Park.
这是我们的装置用来测量温度
So this is our setup for measuring...
以及光透过积雪的成像
temperature and light profiles through the snowpack.
我们做的是利用这种仪器来了解
And what we're doing is using this instrumentation to understand...
积雪里面为雪生藻类所提供的物理环境
the physical conditions within a snowpack...that are able to support snow algae.
今冬这个将会完全埋在雪里
This winter, this will get completely covered in snow and buried.
因此我们将传感器装在这杆子上
And so we have sensors mounted on a pole here.
我们将一些湿敏元件装载这里 这里
So we have some moisture sensors here and here.
而这些小东西就是温度传感器
And then these little ones are just temperature sensors.
然后在杆子的顶端有一个光敏元件
And then at the very top of a pole, we have a light sensor...
用来测量太阳光辐射
which measures incoming solar radiation.
然后在这下面 藏在这个水桶里
And then down here covered in the bucket...
有一个翻斗式雨量计
we have a tipping rain gauge...
用来测量流入这水桶的水量
and this will measure the amount of liquid water...that flows down through this bucket.
我们在这里所看到的雪生藻类
The snow algae that we're seeing here...
繁育在这个温度非常低的环境中
thrives in these very low condition environments.
它很适应零摄氏度的环境
lt's very happy being at zero degrees C.
它很适应低光照的环境
lt's very happy in low-light conditions...
它很适应积雪中的营养贫乏的环境
lt's very happy in the nutrient-poor conditions of a snowpack.
一旦我们了解了在拉森的积雪中
Once we understand the conditions...
生命得以维持的环境
that support life here in the snowpack at Lassen...
那么我们就能对火星积雪进行同样的研究了
then we're also doing studies of snowpacks on Mars.
如果我们在火星上发现同样的环境
And if we find the same conditions on Mars...
你就不得不反问自己
you have to ask yourself the question...
如果地球上的这些积雪是宜居的
well, if these snowpacks on Earth are habitable...
那么火星上的那些积雪是否也会是宜居的呢？
could those snowpacks on Mars also be habitable?
除了火星沟壑外 两个巨大的极地
ln addition to Martian gullies, two massive polar regions...
也有可能成为火星生命的栖息之地
may also be places where life still exists on Mars.
2007年8月4日航天局发射了火星登陆探测器
On August 4, 2007, NASA launched the Phoenix Mars Lander spacecraft.
在它于6月最终抵达这颗红色星球时
When it finally arrives on the red planet in early June...
会探测其冰冻的极地
it will probe its icy poles.
在登陆器上 挖掘沟壑的机械臂
Aboard the craft, robotic arms that dig trenches...
将会铲入冰层
will plow through the layers of water ice...
来观察是否存在有机化合物 生命的元素
to see if there are organic compounds, the building blocks of life.
我们会登陆火星的极地
We might go to the polar regions on Mars...
钻入古冰层提取已经死亡的有机体
drill down into the ancient ice, bring up organisms that are dead.
长期经受着辐射的轰击
They've been shelled by radiation.
然而我们有可能通过研究它们的生物化学
But we might be able to, by studying their biochemistry...
对它们进行修补和重现
patch them back up and resurrect them.
但即使火星上有液态水
But even if Mars holds liquid water...
有无可能曾经维持过大动物的生命呢？
could it have ever sustained larger animal life?
在我们探索太阳系里的地球类生命时
When searching for Earthlike life in our solar system...
科学家期望着液态水和碳的出现
scientists look for the presence of liquid water and carbon.
这些是类地生命的要素
They're crucial ingredients for life on Earth.
但有没有其它指标呢？
But are there other indicators?
一些科学家认为板块运动是
催生生物多样性和
Some scientists believe plate tectonics is necessary to promote biodiversity...
防御大规模的灭绝的必要条件
and act as a defense against mass extinctions.
地球上 板块运动创造了大陆
On Earth, plate-shif ting created continents.
没有大陆板块地球将是一片汪洋
Without land masses, Earth would have remained a water world...
如这样许多物种 包括人类
and, therefore, many species, including humans,
就不可能得到进化
may not have evolved.
那么为何板块运动会存在于地球
So why does plate tectonics exist on Earth...
而不存在于火星这样的其它类地行星上呢？
and not on other terrestrial planets such as Mars?
因为火星小于地球 可能其内部温度冷却得较快
Because Mars is smaller than Earth, likely its interior cooled offfaster.
在其冷却之前实际上火星上也有过板块运动
And it cooled off before, really, plate tectonics were able to start on Mars.
幸运的是 在地球上还存在着板块运动
Fortunately, on Earth, we still have plate tectonics.
板块运动是我们地球的大循环体系
And plate tectonics is the grand recycling system of our planet...
再循环来自大气层 地表 地下的物质
recycling materials from the atmosphere...and the surface and the subsurface...
而火星则永远做不到这一点
and Mars never had that.
板块运动也让地球的温度保持适中
Plate tectonics also keeps Earth's temperatures moderate...
通过再循环化学物质来维持我们大气层里
by recycling chemicals to keep the volume of carbon dioxide...
二氧化碳含量的均衡
in our atmosphere uniform.
没有板块运动就不可能有地球的可持续发展
Lacking plate tectonics, it didn't have the persistence of Earth.
它发展出了潜在的可居住环境
lt developed maybe habitable conditions...
很快发展出了潜在的复杂的多细胞生命
and maybe complex multicellular life very quickly...
然后又消亡了 那是因为它不具备板块运动
and then it dies off because it doesn't have the long-term potential...
给予地球的长期潜能
that plate tectonics gives the Earth.
板块运动或许就是类地生命的一个指标
Plate tectonics may be one indicatorfor Earthlike life.
然而证据表明或许有另一类生命存在于
But evidence suggests there may exist another type of life...
隶属光环之王的一颗卫星上
on a moon that belongs to the Lord of the Rings.
2004年航天局的卡西尼号
ln 2004, NASA's Cassini mission...
进行绕气体巨星土星的飞行
conducted fly-bys around the gas giant planet of Saturn.
一年后 飞船将惠更斯探测器释放到
A year later, the spacecraft released its Huygens probe...
土星最大的卫星土卫六的大气层中
into the atmosphere of Saturn's largest moon, Titan.
图像显示土卫六具有类似地球的特征
The images revealed that Titan has similarfeatures to Earth...
诸如气象周期和火山
such as weather cycles and volcanism.
土星的卫星 土卫六是个很复杂的地方
Saturn's moon, Titan, is a very complex place...
有下雨 河流 季节
with rainfall, rivers, and seasons...
有气象复杂的大气层
and meteorology and a complex atmosphere...
以及有趣的化学变化
and interesting chemistry.
此外 它不会有我们这样的生命
Again, it's not going to be our kind of life...
但是 存在着能量流和有机化合物
but there are flows of energy and organic compounds...
某些其他类型的生命有可能繁育
and some other kind of life could flourish.
雷达图像数据显示出土卫六上存在有液态水
Radar imaging data has revealed the presence of liquid lakes on Titan.
尽管成分是乙烷和甲烷
Although they're comprised of ethane and methane...
但是有可能暗示着40亿年前地球上的水的模样
they may be reminiscent of what water on Earth was like four billion years ago.
土卫六 土星的卫星确实是个寒冷之地
Titan, the moon of Saturn, is a really cool place...
名副其实
literally and figuratively.
非常寒冷 以至于根本不存在液态水
lt's so cold that there is no liquid water.
那里的冰糕坚如磐石
The ice there would be as hard as rocks, water ice...
然而存在着一种液体 液态甲烷 液态乙烷
but there is a liquid... liquid methane, liquid ethane.
或许存在某种生命
So maybe there's life.
可能他们无需液态水
Maybe life doesn't need liquid water.
或许生命可以存在于另一种液体 液态甲烷
Maybe life can survive on another liquid, liquid methane.
土六卫的温度是寒冷的华氏-289度
Titan's temperature is a chilly minus 289 degrees Fahrenheit...
但是它有一个能产生碳氢化合物的富含氮气的大气层
but it has a nitrogen-rich atmosphere which produces hydrocarbons...
能够在较低的温度下保持液态
that can stay liquid at cooler temperatures.
所以有可能土卫六适合
So it's possible that Titan may be hospitable...
一个新物种叫做嗜极生物
to a new type of so-called extremophile...
一种能在极端环境下繁育的生物
an organism that thrives in extreme environments.
在土卫六的情况下它们有可能是嗜冷生物
ln the case of Titan, they may be psychrophiles...
在极端的低温下繁育的细菌
bacteria that thrives in frigid temperatures...
利用甲烷来产出能量
and uses methane to produce energy.
克里斯·麦凯在南极洲的冰封湖底看到过嗜冷生物
Chris McKay has observed psychrophiles...under ice-covered lakes in Antarctica.
某些生物生活在这些水底
Some organisms live at the bottom of these waters...
在那里它们的生物活性产生于这样一个区域
where their biological activities have created a zone...
缺氧富含甲烷这样的有机分子
devoid of oxygen and rich in organic molecules like methane.
南极的生态系统的一个有趣之处
One of the interesting ecosystems in the Antarctic...
就是冰封湖
are the ice-covered lakes...
其持久的冰盖厚约15英尺
which have a persistent ice cover of about fif teen feet of ice.
冰层下存在着液态水
Below that ice, there's liquid water.
存在着水 一点都不惊奇
Given that there's water, it's not too surprising...
水里存在着藻类和细菌
that there's algae and bacteria living in that water.
和南极一样 土卫六的湖泊也可能含有
Like Antarctica, Titan's lakes may also contain...
类似的极端生物靠甲烷生存
similar extreme organisms that survive on methane.
土六卫可能不是唯一的存在生命的卫星
And Titan may not be the only moon harboring life.
2003年航天局的伽利略号太空探测器
ln 2003, NASA's Galileo space probe...
抓拍到了木星的卫星 木卫一的照片
snapped pictures of Jupiter's moon, Europa.
证据表明 液态水有可能存在于其冰封层的下面
Evidence suggests liquid water may exist underneath its frozen crust.
科学家认为 木卫一有一个深度超过50英里的海洋
Scientists think Europa has an ocean that's over fif ty miles deep.
同时还存在着火山活动的迹象
There are also signs ofvolcanic activity.
因此 木卫一的冰水有可能被海底的火山口
So Europa's icy water could be warmed to a liquid state...
融化成液态
by volcanic vents on the ocean floor.
这种火山活动
And this volcanic activity...
将有助于生命获得必需的化学养分
would aid in cooking up chemicals necessary for life.
我们有确凿的证据证明 在冰层下
We have very convincing evidence that below the icy surface...
存在着一个海洋
there's an ocean.
海水 淡水 或许有生命
Ocean water, water, maybe life.
我们还有证据证明
And we also have evidence...
木卫一或许存在着能源
that there are possible energy sources in Europa.
所以生命所需的所有要素似乎都存在
So all the necessary ingredients for life seem to be there.
木卫一表面的冰极厚
The ice on the surface of Europa is extremely thick...
有可能厚达6英里
maybe as much as six miles deep.
因此人类的飞船 不大可能
So it is unlikely that a human spacecraft...
随随便便就钻入到它的海洋中去
will be able to drill down into its ocean anytime soon.
我认为对木卫一的一个现实的任务
l think a realistic mission to Europa...
将会是寻找其表面的生物迹象
would be to search the surface for evidence of organisms...
它们已经透过裂缝 安顿在了表面
that have been carried up through the cracks...and deposited on the surface.
它们有可能已经死了 但是它们是生物
They would be dead, but they would be biological...
我们就可以对其研究了
and we could study them.
我们的太阳系充满了各色有趣之处
Our solar system is full of diverse, interesting places...
我们不应该将任何一处排除有生命
and we shouldn't rule any of them out for life...
直到我们大体探索过了
until we explore broadly...
因为 我们真的不知道我们在找的是什么
'cause we don't really know what we're looking for.
依靠新的科技
Armed with new technologies...
天体生物学家已经拓展了对外星生命的搜寻
astrobiologists have widened their search for extraterrestrial life.
下一个前沿包括我们整个银河系及其以外
The next frontier includes our entire Milky Way galaxy and beyond.
天体生物学正撤回到现代科学的范围
Astrobiology is pushing back the boundaries of modern science.
研究人员现在有了定位日外行星的技术手段
Researchers now have the technological instruments...to locate exoplanets.
这些都是存在于太阳系外的行星
These are planets that exist outside our solar system.
日外行星需要经过若干次测试
Exoplanets need to pass several tests...
目的是为了审视是否适合类地生命
in order to be considered suitable for Earthlike life.
最重要的是它们需要在一个适宜居住的地带
Most importantly, they need to be within a habitable zone...
中央有一颗恒星 就像我们有太阳能以保持有液态水
of a central star, like our Sun, in order to support liquid water.
我们的恒星恰到好处
Our star is just right.
不是太热也不是太冷
lt's not too hot, and it's not too cold.
所以 我们就恰好处在这个生命得以进化的理想之地
And so we're just right in this perfect area where life was able to evolve.
2008年航天局发射了一个太空望远镜叫做开普勒
ln 2008, NASA plans to launch a space telescope called Kepler...
来搜索地球般大小的类地行星
to search for terrestrial Earth-sized planets.
航天器上的仪器能够侦测到日外行星
The spacecraft's instruments will be able to detect exoplanets...
通过测量恒星的光变曲线的变化
by measuring changes in a star"s light curve...
一旦行星在恒星与航天器之间经过
as a planet passes between the star and the spacecraft.
杰夫·马西是世界上主要的行星猎手之一
Geoff Marcy is one of the world's leading planet hunters.
我们估计光我们的银河系就有约500亿
We would estimate that there are some fif ty billion...
或者600亿颗类地行星
maybe sixty billion Earthlike planets...within just our Milky Way galaxy alone...
别忘了我们的银河系
and remember, our Milky Way galaxy...
只是数百上千亿个星系中的一个
is just one of hundreds of billions of galaxies out there...
它们都差不多与银河系相仿
more or less like our Milky Way.
因此我们宇宙中的类地行星的数量
So the number of Earthlike planets in our universe...
几乎是不计其数的
is a nearly uncountable number.
然而找到日外行星对于天体生物学来说只成功了一半
But locating exoplanets is only half the battle for an astrobiologist.
在未来的20年里
ln the next twenty years...
航天局将会发射类地行星探测器
NASAwill launch the Terrestrial Planet Finder.
这个高灵敏太空望远镜的集合体
This collection of highly sensitive space telescopes...
将会确认行星是否具有合适的大气层气体
will actually recognize if a planet has the right atmospheric gases...
比如水蒸汽 二氧化碳 甲烷 臭氧
such as water vapor, carbon dioxide, methane, and ozone...
所有维持类地生命所必需的物质
all necessary to sustain Earthlike life.
有了图像我们就能拿着那颗行星所发出的光
With that picture, we can then take the light from that planet...
将其延展成各种颜色或波长
spread it out into all of its colors or wavelengths:
蓝 绿 黄 红甚至到红外线
blue, green, yellow, red, even to the infrared...
分析那光的化学成分
and analyze that light for the chemical composition...
甚至还有可能那颗行星的生物成分
maybe even the biological composition of that planet.
我们就有可能发现各种生命的痕迹
What we might find are signs of life in a variety offorms.
比如氧气
For example, oxygen.
要产生大型类地生命
When it comes to producing larger Earthlike life...
行星或卫星就离不开氧气了
a planet or moon needs oxygen.
34亿年前我们地球唯一的生命
3.4 billion years ago, the only life on our planet...
是单细胞微生物
were single-celled microbial organisms.
但是随着这个原始生命吸收太阳能
But as this primitive life absorbed energy from the sun...
它形成了一种绿色色素叫做叶绿素
it formed a green pigment called chlorophyll.
这就产生了光合作用 一种化学过程
This produced photosynthesis, a chemical process...
能将二氧化碳和水转化成能量
which converts carbon dioxide and water into energy...
同时氧气作为其废产物
with oxygen as a waste product.
单细胞生物进化成蓝细菌
Single-celled organisms evolved into cyanobacteria...
地球上最早的生物结构
one of the Earth's earliest structures.
蓝细菌将大量的氧注入到海洋和大气中
Cyanobacteria injected vast amounts of oxygen into the oceans and air.
新生命出现了 经过多样化和进化
New life emerged, which diversified and developed...
变成了众多的多细胞物种 最终变成了人
into large, multicellular species and, eventually, man.
我们的地球大气层中就会没有氧气
Our Earth would not have oxygen in the atmosphere...
只要没有植物的生长
if it were not for plant life, by photosynthesis...
光合作用所产生的氧气就会氧化岩石而消失殆尽
generating the oxygen that other wise would oxidize rocks and vanish.
所以氧是地球的生物标志
So oxygen is a biomarker for the Earth.
如果我们能够审视另一颗类地行星
lfwe could examine another Earthlike planet...
并在其大气层里发现氧气
and detect oxygen in its atmosphere...
那就成了一个关键的标记 但还不是决定性的
it would be one key sign... not yet definitive...
而是争论的一个要素
but one element of the argument...
那就是 行星也还要有光合作用的生命
that that planet, too, has photosynthetic life.
在航天局的阿姆斯研究中心
At NASA's Ames Research Center...
天体化学家李·倍布特及其同事
astrochemist Lee Bebout and her colleagues...
正在一个温室里培养含氧生态系统
are cultivating oxygen-bearing ecosystems in a greenhouse.
这些是微生物垫 复杂的微生物群落
They're microbial mats, complex microbe communities...
常见于高盐度水体和碳酸盐海滩的
often found on muddy and sandy sediment surfaces...
淤泥和沙质的沉积物表面
in hyper-salty waters and carbonate beaches.
这些微生物垫是地球上已知最古老的生态系统
These microbial mats are the oldest known living ecosystems on Earth.
倍布特想知道 这些有可能存在于其他行星的微生物是否
Bebout wants to know if these microbes could exist on other planets...
会产生氧气 从而让生命得以进化
producing oxygen, thereby enabling life to evolve.
我们知道随着氧气生产的出现
We know that, with the advent of oxygen production...
通过光合作用这些微生物生态系统
through photosynthesis, these microbial ecosystems...
尤其是蓝细菌开始改变我们的大气层
in particular the cyanobacteria, began to change our atmosphere.
我们非常好奇那是如何发生的？是如何变迁的？
We're very curious how that happened, how that transitioned...
是如何改造和传播的？
how these microbes adapted and spread...
到种类繁多充斥了我们地球的各个地方
to diversif y and fill so many niches on our planet.
这很重要 有助于我们判定要找的那些行星
This is important in helping us decide what to look for on other places...
也就是火星或其它日外行星
say, Mars or other extraterrestrial places.
如果生命存在于我们银河系或遥远的星系里
lf life exists far off in our galaxy or in distant galaxies...
那么它真的会是地球这样的呢？
will it truly be Earthlike?
在我们地球上所有的生命都具有DNA
On our planet, all life contains DNA...
掌握每一个生命蓝本的一长串分子
a long chain of molecules that holds the blueprint for every living thing.
它使得生命复制和分枝
lt allows life to duplicate and branch out...
实质上是在创造生命之树
essentially creating the tree of life.
然而存不存在选择呢？
But are there alternatives?
或许另外的世界里的生命 还是碳水为基的
Maybe life on another world is still carbon and water-based...
但是根本就不适用DNA
but doesn't use DNA at all.
或许它使用完全不同的分子类型来存储信息
Maybe it uses a completely different type of molecule to store information.
那将是非常让人兴奋的
That would be very exciting.
那有无可能存在无需DNA 碳 水的生命呢？
And could there be life that doesn't require DNA, carbon, or water?
有可能我们地球是那种蹩脚的行星
lt may be that ours is kind of a crappy planet...
相反外面的行星
compared to what's out there...
有可能存在着其他行星
that there may be other planets...
对于高等生命要更加适宜得多
that are much more optimized for advanced life.
我好多做天体生物学研究的同事
Many of my colleagues, which are doing astrobiological research...
他们在寻找的生命 说的刻薄点 我要说可能是傻瓜生命
they're looking for life that, unkindly, l might typif y as stupid life.
他们多半是在寻找微生物
They're looking for microbes mostly.
或许是稍微大一点的东西
There may be something a little bit bigger.
有些天体生物学家希望不期碰上
Some astrobiologists want a close encounter...
的东西不只是微生物
with something more than just a microbe.
他们寻找的智能生命或许甚至比我们还要聪明
They're looking for intelligent life that's perhaps even smarter than us.
生命的探寻已不止寻找粘糊糊的细菌
The search for life extends beyond looking for slimy bacteria.
在天体生物学中 一队技艺高超的科学家
ln astrobiology, a crack team of scientists...
希望接触到更加显赫的东西
wants to make contact with something much grander.
搜寻地外文明 [SETI] 顾名思义 就是搜寻太空智能生命
SETl, of course, is looking for intelligent life in space...
但是并不止于此
but it doesn't just stop there.
他们必须不光是有智慧
They have to be not only intelligent...
而且他们还必须具有科技能力
but they have to be technologically competent.
搜寻地外文明
The Search for Extraterrestrial lntelligence lnstitute...
简称SETI 利用无线电技术
better known as SETl, uses radio technology...
监听外星文明的无线电泄漏
to listen for radio leaks from alien civilizations.
其基于的假设是人类需要沟通
lt's based on the premise that humans need to communicate.
因此 或许外星人种也希望传送他们的信息
So perhaps alien nations also want to get their message out.
我们争取做的只是尽力监听信号
What we try and do is simply try and eavesdrop on signals...
我们用天线截获的无线电波
either radio waves that we could pick up with our antennas...
还有闪烁的激光
orflashing laser lights.
他们可能会利用强大的激光器对准我们的方向发射光束
They might be using big lasers to aim pulses of light in our direction.
我不是人类
l am not man.
我是微生物
l am microbe.
我还是来自搜寻地外文明研究所的塞思·肖斯塔克
l'm also Seth Shostak for the SETl lnstitute...
我们的任务是了解
whose mission is to understand...
宇宙生命的属性和起源
the nature and origin of life in the universe.
我是莫莉·本特利 欢迎收听"我们孤独吗？"
And l'm Molly Bentley. Welcome to "Are We Alone?"
我们要提醒你 生命要多于你在当地动物园所看到的
We'll remind you that there's more to life...than just what you find at your local zoo.
在搜寻地外文明研究所资深天文学家塞思·肖斯塔克
At SETl, senior astronomer Seth Shostak...
主持一档定期的播客广播节目
hosts a regular radio show that's podcasted.
我们正在监听微生物
We're buggin' out with microbes.
全都与你相伴在一起
There are so many cohabitating with you.
你在收听的是"给我一个细菌"
You're listening to "Hand Me A Microbe."
肖斯塔克主持节目生动活泼
Shostak broadcasts lively...
然而 在将科学有关的消息提供给地球人的同时
yet informative science-related news to Earthlings...
其他高等文明也有能力收听到
as well as other advanced civilizations that have the means to listen in.
辛西娅·菲利普斯 感谢你的加入
Cynthia Phillips, thanks forjoining me today.
我们非常喜欢电台的收听
We are so fond of radio for listening...
我们创办每周一次的广播节目 某种意义上是在播送
that we started a weekly radio show in which we, in a sense, broadcast.
很多人对搜寻地外文明感兴趣
There are a lot of people who are interested in SETl...
因为大家对外星人的兴趣不亚于
because everybody's interested in aliens in the same way...
对恐龙的兴趣
that just about everybody's interested in dinosaurs.
人们就是对此感兴趣
People are just interested in that.
因此我们努力利用这样一个事实
So we're trying to take advantage of the fact...
他们对我们做的感兴趣
that they're interested in what we do...
让他们感兴趣于某些更广泛的主题
to get them interested in some broader subjects...
对科学和技术
in science and also technology.
搜寻地外文明 自1960年代以来就一直在监听信号
SETl has been listening for signals since the 1960s...
然而 从未收到过外星人来的讯息
but E.T. hasn't phoned in.
这种沉默已经激起了怀疑
This silence has fueled skepticism.
我们会发现很多具有生命的行星
And we're going to find lots of planets with life.
我猜测智慧相当罕见
l'm guessing that intelligence will be rare...
但是他们将和人类一样聪明
but they won't be smart in the way that humans are smart.
那将是罕见的
That's going to be rare.
但是另一方面那只是我的直觉
But, again, that's just my intuition.
外星人不可能快于光速到达这里
Aliens can't get here faster than the speed of light.
物理学不允许那样
Physics doesn't allow that.
那就意味着由于我们的广播仅仅只有60年
And that means, since we've only been broadcasting...for, say, sixty years...
他们是不可能来自30光年以外的行星
they can't be coming from a planet more than thirty light-years away.
30光年以内的恒星数量是相当少的
Well, the number of stars within thirty light-years is pretty small.
我们的宇宙已经超过120亿年了
Our universe is over twelve billion years old.
行星地球只有约46亿多年
Planet Earth has only been around for over 4.6 billion years.
因此 存在着比我们年长数百万甚至数十亿年的行星
Therefore, there are planets millions and billions of years older than us.
如果银河系外存在着生命的话
So, if there's life beyond the Milky Way galaxy...
就极有可能比我们先进数百万甚至数十亿年
it potentially could be millions...to billions of years more advanced than us.
我认为外面确实存在着智能物种
l think that the truly intelligent species out there...
如果他们曾经和我们不期相遇
if they ever happened upon us...
那么 看待我们可能就像我们看待蚂蚁和细菌那样
would maybe regard us as we regard ants or bacteria...
作为生命的某种原始样本
as some primitive example of life.
我们遇到的东西会比我们先进得多
Anybody we meet is going to be much more advanced than us...
至少肯定在文明的历史方面比我们历史悠久得多
at least certainly much more aged than us...in terms of how long they have been a civilization.
如果智慧文明确实存在于地球之外
lf intelligent civilizations do exist beyond Earth...
那么他们的模样会怎样呢？
what would they look like?
如果我们在太空中找到智能生命
lf we find intelligence in space...
其表现会超出生物智能
it's moved on beyond biological intelligence...
而倾向机器智能
and moved on to machine intelligence.
有思想的机器代表了超越我们百万年的进化
A thinking machine that represents a million years' evolution...beyond where we are.
谁知道它是如何打造的？
Who knows how it's built?
你所知道的一切 就是它有可能非常非常的聪明
All you know is that it might be really, really smart.
不存在合乎逻辑的理由 认为来自其他世界的机器
There's no logical reason why there shouldn't be machines...
不应该来探索我们的星球
from other worlds exploring our planet...
进入我们的领空
coming into our airspace...
甚至可能会以某种方式与我们互动
maybe even attempting to interact with us in some way.
无论我们发现了细菌的踪迹还是高科技文明
Whether we find a trace of bacteria or a high-tech civilization...
所有生命的发现都将彻底变革
any discovery of life will revolutionize...
我们对宇宙以及我们自身的认识
the way we think about the universe and ourselves.
在此之前 那始终是最大的未解之谜之一
Until then, it remains...one of the greatest unsolved mysteries of all time.
我们将看到外面一个真实的动物园
And we're going to see a real zoo out there...
一旦我们最终真的发现了外星生命
when we finally do discover alien life.
各种不同的信息编码的方式
All sorts of different ways of coding information...
制造出了分子 产生了生命现象
and making molecules, causing the phenomenon of life.
致力于这个领域的人都是怪人
The people that work on this field are geeks...
所以 我们来想象一下与外星怪人的沟通 好吗？
so we imagine making contact with alien geeks, right?
我们将一起愉快地讨论方程式
And that we're going to have fun talking about equations together...
但是 我们或许会最终与外星时尚人士或嬉皮士接触
but maybe we'll end up making contact...with alien hipsters or bohemians...
我们会需要某些其它论坛
and we'll need some other forum.
所以 生命 只是我们不知道
So, life as we don't know it.
非常感谢和我的交流
Thanks very much for talking with me.
我是塞思·肖斯塔克 来自搜寻地外文明研究所
l'm Seth Shostak for the SETl institute...
我们一直在监听
where we always listen...
但是 偶尔 我们也会广播
but, occasionally, we broadcast.
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing